Guide to the Charles Hill Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Writings
  - World Order
    - Europe, 2013 (Box 61, Folder 4-5)
    - Idea for book, 2013 (Box 61, Folder 6)
    - Notes on "Europe" chapter, 2013 May 25 (Box 61, Folder 7)
    - The questions, 2013 (Box 61, Folder 8)
    - The story (chapter outline), 2014 April 7 (Box 61, Folder 9)
    - Technology, 2013 (Box 61, Folder 10)
    - Writings related to World Order, 2013 (Box 61, Folder 11)
- Notebooks
  Series VI contains copies of Hill's notebooks kept during his tenure in the United States State Department from 1978-1989. The notebooks chronicle events confronting the administration of Ronald Reagan and offer a detailed overview of decision-making on diplomacy and U.S. foreign policy. Hill later reviewed the notebooks and attached post-it notes to mark the subjects of the entries. Copies of these post-it notes appear in this series. No notebooks exist between the years 1980-1982. Notebooks maintained by Hill for 1987 are not present in the collection and are presumably lost.
  Series VI is arranged alphabetically.
  - 1979 September 12--1979 November 16 (Box 62, Folder 1)
  - 1979 November 19–1980 March 7 (Box 62, Folder 2)
  - 1982 December 13–1983 January 28 (Box 62, Folder 3)
  - 1983 February 14–1983 April 1 (Box 62, Folder 4)
  - 1983 April 2–1983 April 22 (Box 62, Folder 5)
  - 1983 May 10–1983 June 21 (Box 62, Folder 6)
  - 1983 June 21–1983 July 29 (Box 62, Folder 7)
  - 1983 August 1–1983 September 1 (Box 63, Folder 1)
  - 1983 September 1–1983 October 15 (Box 63, Folder 2)
  - 1983 October 13–1983 November 22 (Box 63, Folder 3)
  - 1983 November 23–1983 December 31 (Box 63, Folder 4)
  - 1984 January 1–1984 January 27 (Box 63, Folder 5)
  - 1984 January 28–1984 February 19 (Box 63, Folder 6)
  - 1984 February 20–1984 April 6 (Box 64, Folder 1)
  - 1984 April 6–1984 May 24 (Box 64, Folder 2)
  - 1984 May 24–1984 June 28 (Box 64, Folder 3)
  - 1984 June 29–1984 July 30 (Box 64, Folder 4)
  - 1984 August 5–1984 September 5 (Box 64, Folder 5)
  - 1984 September 6–1984 September 30 (Box 64, Folder 6)
  - 1984 October 1–1984 October 31 (Box 65, Folder 1)
  - 1984 November 1–1984 November 28 (Box 65, Folder 2)
  - 1984 November 28–1984 December 26 (Box 65, Folder 3)
  - 1984 December 26–1985 January 23 (Box 65, Folder 4)
  - 1985 January 23–1985 February 19 (Box 65, Folder 5)
  - 1985 February 20–1985 April 1 (Box 65, Folder 6)
  - 1985 April 1–1985 April 30 (Box 65, Folder 7)
  - 1985 May 1–1985 May 24 (Box 66, Folder 1)
  - 1985 May 24–1985 June 14 (Box 66, Folder 2)
  - 1985 June 15–1985 July 3 (Box 66, Folder 3)
  - 1985 July 3–1985 August 6 (Box 66, Folder 4)
  - 1985 August 6–1985 September 19 (Box 66, Folder 5)
  - 1985 September 20–1985 October 10 (Box 66, Folder 6)
  - 1985 October 10–1985 November 4 (Box 67, Folder 1)
  - 1985 November 4–1985 November 29 (Box 67, Folder 2)
  - 1985 November 30–1986 January 6 (Box 67, Folder 3)
  - 1986 January 6–1986 January 23 (Box 67, Folder 4)
  - 1986 January 23–1986 February 6 (Box 67, Folder 5)
  - 1986 February 7–1986 February 26 (Box 67, Folder 6)
  - 1986 February 26–1986 March 20 (Box 68, Folder 1)
  - 1986 March 21–1986 April 14 (Box 68, Folder 2)
  - 1986 April 14–1986 May 12 (Box 68, Folder 3)
  - 1986 May 12–1986 June 2 (Box 68, Folder 4)
  - 1986 June 2–1986 June 28 (Box 68, Folder 5)
  - 1986 June 28–1986 July 24 (Box 68, Folder 6)
  - 1986 July 24–1986 September 4 (Box 68, Folder 7)
  - 1986 September 5–1986 September 24 (Box 69, Folder 1)
  - 1986 September 24–1986 October 17 (Box 69, Folder 2)
  - 1986 October 18–1986 November 4 (Box 69, Folder 3)
  - 1986 November 4–1986 November 19 (Box 69, Folder 4)
  - 1988 January 18–1988 January 31 (Box 69, Folder 5)
  - 1988 January 30–1988 February 22 (Box 69, Folder 6)
  - 1988 February 22–1988 March 9 (Box 69, Folder 7)
  - 1988 March 9–1988 March 31 (Box 70, Folder 1)
  - 1988 March 31–1988 April 3 (Box 70, Folder 2)
  - 1988 April 3–1988 April 20 (Box 70, Folder 3)
  - 1988 April 21–1988 May 10 (Box 70, Folder 4)
  - 1988 May 10–1988 May 23 (Box 70, Folder 5)
  - 1988 May 23–1988 June 10 (Box 70, Folder 6)
  - 1988 June 13–1988 June 30 (Box 70, Folder 7)
  - 1988 June 30–1988 July 26 (Box 71, Folder 1)
  - 1988 July 26–1988 September 7 (Box 71, Folder 2)
  - 1988 September 8–1988 September 29 (Box 71, Folder 3)
  - 1988 September 29–1988 October 31 (Box 71, Folder 4)
  - 1988 October 31–1988 November 22 (Box 71, Folder 5)
  - 1988 November 22–1988 December 13 (Box 71, Folder 6)
  - 1988 December 13–1989 January 13 (Box 71, Folder 7)
  - 1989 January 13–1989 January 19 (Box 71, Folder 8)
- Restricted
  Series VII is comprised of restricted materials. Materials include correspondence with Henry Kissinger and George Shultz, administrative files pertaining to the Brady-Johnson Program in Grand Strategy, and Hill's notebooks and desk diaries.
  Correspondence and subject files related to Henry Kissinger and George Shultz are closed to researchers until five years after the date of Kissinger's and Shultz's deaths, respectively. The administrative files (containing information on the Brady-Johnson program in Grand Strategy, academic appointments, and other departmental issues) are closed for 35 years. Hill's personal notebooks and desk diaries contain student names and grades and are therefore closed for 75 years.
  Series VII is arranged alphabetically.
  - Correspondence
    Conditions Governing Access
    Correspondence in this series is restricted until 5 years after the date of Henry Kissinger's and George Shultz's deaths, per donor request.
    - Kissinger, Henry, 2007–2016 (Box 72, Folder 1-3)
    - Kissinger, Henry, 2017 (Box 73, Folder 1)
    - Kissinger, Henry--letter on Charles Hill book, 2009 (Box 73, Folder 2)
    - Kissinger, Henry - On World Order (with drafts), 2013–2014 (Box 73, Folder 3-4)
    - Kissinger, Henry--Russia trip, 2016 (Box 73, Folder 5)
    - Shultz, George, 1990–2016 (Box 73, Folder 6)
    - Shultz, George--"Decline of Diplomacy", 1997 (Box 73, Folder 7)
    - Shultz, George--"Riverbed", 2002 (Box 73, Folder 8)
  - Research Materials and Subject Files
    Research Materials and Subject Files in this series are restricted until 5 years after the date of Henry Kissinger's and George Shultz's deaths, per donor request.
    - Henry Kissinger, "The Meaning of History" (doctoral dissertation), 1950 (Box 74, Folder 1-3)
    - Kissinger, Henry--On World Order: United States, 2013 (Box 74, Folder 4)
    - "One State or Two?" Hoover Conference, 2015 (Box 74, Folder 5)
    - Report by Schuyler Schouten on The Trial of Henry Kissinger, 2003–2005 (Box 74, Folder 6)
    - Schuyler Schouten, "Interview with Dr. Henry Kissinger", 2003 (Box 74, Folder 7)
    - World Order: Charles Hill paper to Henry A. Kissinger, 2012–2013 (Box 74, Folder 8)
  - Writings
    Writings in this series are restricted until 5 years after the date of Henry Kissinger's and George Shultz's deaths, per donor request.
    - "Governing Diversity", 2013–2014 (Box 74, Folder 9)
    - Notes on roundtable disussions of American foreign policy--Stanford University, 2012–2016 (Box 74, Folder 10)
  - Administrative Files
    Administrative records in this series is restricted 35 years per Yale Corporation guidelines.
    - Brady-Johnson Program in Grand Strategy--Annual reports, 2012–2016 (Box 75, Folder 1)
    - Bunker Prize --Yale, 1994 (Box 75, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence on Kissinger papers, 2011–2013 (Box 75, Folder 3)
    - GS (Grand Strategy): "A Committee on Strategic Thought?", 2015 (Box 75, Folder 4)
    - GS (Grand Strategy): Blue brothers/New ideas, 2007 (Box 75, Folder 5)
    - GS (Grand Strategy): Decisions, 2014 (Box 75, Folder 6)
    - GS (Grand Strategy): Vision, 2016 (Box 75, Folder 7)
    - ISS(International Security Studies)/GS (Grand Strategy) organization chart, 2012 (Box 75, Folder 8)
    - ISS (International Security Studies) board meeting, 1997 June 14 (Box 75, Folder 9)
    - Kissinger papers to Yale, 2011 (Box 75, Folder 10)
    - Norma Thompson, 2001 (Box 75, Folder 11)
    - Tenure and administrative positions at Yale, 2000–2001 (Box 75, Folder 12)
  - Notebooks
    Notebooks in this series is restricted for 75 years per Yale Corporation guidelines.
    - 1993–1998 (Box 76, Folder 1)
    - 2010 (Box 76, Folder 2)
    - 2011 (Box 76, Folder 3)
    - 2012 (Box 76, Folder 4)
    - 2014 (Box 76, Folder 5)
    - 2016 (Box 76, Folder 6)
  - Desk Diaries
    Desk Diaries in this series is restricted for 75 years per Yale Corporation guidelines.
    - 1997 (Box 77, Folder 1)
    - 1998 (Box 77, Folder 2)
    - 1999 (Box 77, Folder 3)
    - 2000 (Box 77, Folder 4)
    - 2001 (Box 77, Folder 5)
    - 2002 (Box 77, Folder 6)
    - 2003 (Box 77, Folder 7)
    - 2004 (Box 77, Folder 8)
    - 2005 (Box 77, Folder 9)
    - 2006 (Box 78, Folder 1)
    - 2007 (Box 78, Folder 2)
    - 2008 (Box 78, Folder 3)
    - 2009 (Box 78, Folder 4)
    - 2010 (Box 78, Folder 5)
    - 2011 (Box 79, Folder 1)
    - 2012 (Box 79, Folder 2)
    - 2013 (Box 79, Folder 3)
    - 2014 (Box 79, Folder 4)
    - 2015 (Box 79, Folder 5)
- Additional materials, 1997-2018; 2005-2018; Accession 2019-M-0007; 3.34; (9 boxes); The accession consists of the personal papers of Charles Hill. Materials include Hill's correspondence, including correspondence with former United States secretaries of state Henry Kissinger and George Shultz. The accession also consists of writings, including book reviews and commentary articles on United States foreign policy, and course material from Hill's class "Oratory in Statecraft" taught at Yale University, 2006-2018.
  The accession is arranged into four headings: Correspondence, Course materials for Oratory in Statecraft, Writings, and Restricted files.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Charles Hill, 2018.
  Correspondence with Henry Kissinger and George Shultz is closed until five years after the deaths of Dr. Henry A. Kissinger and Secretary of State George Shultz. Additional correspondence with Henry Kissinger identified by the donor is closed until twenty-five years after the death of Dr. Henry A. Kissinger. Correspondence with Yale University is closed for thirty-five years per Yale Corporation guidelines. Material containing student grades are restricted until 2093 as established by Yale Corporation regulations http://web.library.yale.edu/mssa/collections/research-use-of-yale-university-archives.
  - Correspondence
    - A-C, 2016-2018 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - D-I, 2016-2018 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - J-Q, 2013-2018 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - R-Z, 2017-2018 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Course materials for Oratory in Statecraft
    - Annan, Kofi, farewell address, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Bacon, Francis, "What is the Chief Part of an Orator?", 2005 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Boorstin, Daniel, The Americans: The National Experience, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Buckley, William F., "Notes from the Lecture Circuit", undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Bush, George W., speech on New Orleans, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - China- why boring speeches?, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Churchill, Winston, by Isaiah Berlin, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Cicero, first and third Catilinarian Oration, commentary, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Cicero, third Catilinarian Oration, commentary, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Cicero, De Oratore, commentary, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Cicero, Pro Marcello, commentary, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Cicero, Pro Milone, commentary, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Cicero, Pro Murena, commentary, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Communist Manifesto, 2009-2014 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Course contents, 2015 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Course readings, 2018 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Crisis cases used in grand strategies simulation in the Yale-National University of Singapore College, 2018 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Decay of Eloquence at Rome in the First Century, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Deliberation and persuasion, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Democracy, 2007-2010 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Demosthenes, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Deportment, 2007-2014 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Edwards, Jonathan, "Sinners in the Hands of an Angry God", 2003-2005 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Eisenhower, Dwight, farewell address, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Embassy to Achilles, Debate at Sparta, Milton/Pandæmonium, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Emerson: Eloquence, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Exercises, oratory, National Day, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Ford, Gerald, Dick Cheney eulogy, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - The Gettysburg Address, 2008-2010 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Gorgias, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Hill, Katie, speeches, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Hitler, Adolf, oratory, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Homer, Embassy to Achilles, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - The Importance of Untenable Theories, Freud's Primal Statecraft, 2011-2014 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - The Jeremaid, also David Lyle Jeffrey, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - King, Martin Luther, Jr., 2003-2005 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Kissinger, Henry, international law speech, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Khrushchev, Nikita, secret speech, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Lecture and daily topic book, 2005-2018 (Box 3, Folder 14-16)
    - Lecture notes, 2007-2016 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - "Like" and "no problem", 2007-2015 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Lincoln, Abraham oratory, 2010-2013 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - MacArthur, Douglas, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Marcus, Greil, three speeches by John Winthrop, Abraham Lincoln, Martin Luther King Jr., 2006 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - The Marshall Plan, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Memes, 2007-2014 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Milton, John: Machiavellian Rhetoric in Paradise Lost, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Milton, John: Richard Arnold, Logic of the Fall, on the speeches in Pandæmonium, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Milton, John: Speeches at Pandæmonium, Stanley Fish commentary on Belial, 2006 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Modern speeches, Martin Luther King Jr. "I Have a Dream", George W. Bush State of the Union 2003, 2002-2006 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - The New Age of Oratory and Islamism vs World Order, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Noonan, Peggy, "Logic", undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Obama, Barack, articles and notes, 2008-2010 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Obama, Barack, Nobel Peace Prize speech, 2009-2010 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Obama, Barack, speech to the Muslim world, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Oratory articles, 2005-2018 (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
    - Oratory course proposal, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Oratory introductory notes for mini-lectures, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Oratory, surroundings, words, gaffs, and key images, 2007-2018 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Oratory syllabus, 2012 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Patton, George, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Pericles, and Plato, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Poe, Edgar Allen, pages of Catalogue on Rhetoric, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Presentation of self in everyday life, men, 2007-2016 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Presentation of self in everyday life, women, 2008-2013 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - The Primal Horde: Freud's Statement and Social Contract, 2011-2014 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Published articles with annotations by Charles Hill, 1998-2017 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Pure reason/right reason, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Reagan, Ronald radio talk, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Rhetoric
      - Aristotle, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Bibliography, 2005-2006 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Confucius from ritual to rhetoric, first session, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Edmund Burke, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
      - The Ends of Puritan Rhetoric, Sacvan Bercovitch, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
      - George H. W. Bush, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      - The Jeremiad, The language of Salem witchcraft, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
      - John Brown, undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
      - King James Bible, 2006-2010 (Box 5, Folder 18)
      - Las Casas and Niccolo Machiavelli, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 19)
      - Lincoln-Douglas debates, preface/intro by Harry Jaffa, Crisis of the House Divided, 2007 (Box 5, Folder 20)
      - Lincoln metaphors, 2003-2007 (Box 5, Folder 21)
      - Rhetoric, Norma Thompson course, 2005-2006 (Box 5, Folder 22)
      - Rhetoric of performance in Rome, Staging Masculinity, 2000-2001 (Box 5, Folder 23)
      - The Speech of the Athenians at Sparta by A.E. Raubitschek, 2006 (Box 5, Folder 24)
      - Yale University, Rollin G. Osterweis course, "The History of American Oratory", 2004-2005 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Robespierre, Maximilien, undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Robespierre the orator, undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Saxonhouse, Arlene, "Free Speech and Democracy in Ancient Athens", undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - The Sermon on the Mount, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Shultz, George P., Bitburg, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Shultz, George P., Park Avenue Synagogue Address, undated (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Speeches package, George Marshall, Martin Luther King Jr., Henry Kissinger, 2010 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Speechwriting, 2002-2011 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - State of the Union, 2007-2014 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - State of the Union, presidential complexity, 2009-2010 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Statesmen and Demogogues, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Summary of classical thought on oratory from noble lie to Aristotle's 3 forms, 2007 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Thucydides: Nicias and Alcibiades in their speeches, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Thucydides rhetoric, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Valentine exercise, 2015 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Voice in politics, 2007-2008 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Washington and grand strategy, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Washington, George, 2006-2007 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - The Western Ciceronian oratorical tradition, 2004-2009 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Whitman, Walt, and Abraham Lincoln, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Whitman, Walt, and oratory, Aztecs and others, 2006 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Writings
    - Book reviews, 2017-2018 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Commentary articles for the Hoover Institute, 2017-2018 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Hoover Institute conferences and colloquiums, 2015-2018 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - "Language: The Most Disruptive Technology", for Hoover Institute conference on disruptive technologies, Stanford University, 2017 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - On Ken Burns's "Vietnam", 2017 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Restricted
    Series IV consists of restricted files. Correspondence with Henry Kissinger and George Shultz is closed until five years after the deaths of Dr. Henry A. Kissinger and Secretary of State George Shultz. Additional correspondence with Henry Kissinger identified by the donor is closed until twenty-five years after the death of Dr. Henry A. Kissinger. Correspondence with Yale University is closed for thirty-five years per Yale Corporation guidelines. Material containing student grades are restricted until 2093 as established by Yale Corporation regulations http://web.library.yale.edu/mssa/collections/research-use-of-yale-university-archives.
    - Correspondence
      - Kissinger, Henry, 2012-2018 (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
        Correspondence is closed until five years after the death of Dr. Henry A. Kissinger.
      - Kissinger, Henry, 2012-2018 (Box 9, Folder 1)
        Closed until twenty-five years after the death of Dr. Henry A. Kissinger.
      - Shultz, George, 2012-2018 (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
        Correspondence is closed until five years after the death of George Shultz.
      - Yale University, 2012-2015 (Box 9, Folder 4)
        Correspondence with Yale University is restricted 35 years per Yale Corporation guidelines
    - Course material
      Files containing student grades are restricted until 2093 as established by Yale Corporation regulations http://web.library.yale.edu/mssa/collections/research-use-of-yale-university-archives.
      - Lecture and daily topic book, 2005-2018 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Oratory examination material, 2007-2016 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Personal notebook, 2017-2018 (Box 9, Folder 7)